I thought I would think about changing your perspective on the world a bit,
أود أن أغير رؤيتكم عن العالم قليلا
and showing you some of the designs that we have in nature.
وأعرض عليكم بعض التصاميم التي عندنا عن الطبيعة.
And so, I have my first slide to talk about
سأتحدث في هذه الصورة الأولى
the dawning of the universe and what I call
عن بزوغ الكون وما أسميه
the cosmic scene investigation, that is, looking at
بحث المشهد الكوني أو النظر في
the relics of creation and inferring what happened at the beginning,
بقايا البعث (الخلق) لإستنتاج ما حدث في البداية
and then following it up and trying to understand it.
ومن ثم تتبع ذلك لمحاولة فهم ما حدث.
And so one of the questions that I asked you is,
ولذا واحد من الاسئلة التي طرحتها
when you look around, what do you see?
عندما تحدقون النظر، ماذا ترون؟
Well, you see this space that's created by designers
حسنا، ترون هذا الفضاء المشكل عن طريق مصممين
and by the work of people, but what you actually see
والناس ولكن في الحقيقة ما ترونه
is a lot of material that was already here,
عبارة عن مواد كانت موجودة هنا أصلا
being reshaped in a certain form.
وتمت إعادة تصميمها بشكل محدد.
And so the question is: how did that material get here?
وعليه السؤال الذي يطرح نفسه، كيف وصلت هذه المواد هنا؟
How did it get into the form that it had before it got reshaped, and so forth?
كيف تشكلت بالشكل الذي عليه قبل ان يتم اعادة تشكيلها وهلم جرا؟
It's a question of what's the continuity?
انه سؤال في الحقيقة عن ما هي الاستمرارية؟
So one of the things I look at is,
لذا واحد من الاشياء التي ابحث عنها
how did the universe begin and shape?
كيف بدأ الكون؟ وكيف تشكل؟
What was the whole process in the creation and the evolution of the universe
كيف تمت عملية البعث والتطور في الكون
to getting to the point that we have these kinds of materials?
الى النقطة التي تكونت عندها هذه المواد؟
So that's sort of the part, and let me move on then and show you
لذا هذا هو جزء البحث الى حد ما، ودعوني أمضي لأريكم
the Hubble Ultra Deep Field.
مجال هابل عن الفضاء البعيد.
If you look at this picture,
اذا نظرت في هذه الصورة
what you will see is a lot of dark with some light objects in it.
سترى الكثير من الظلام المصحوب ببعض الاجسام المضيئة.
And everything but -- four of these light objects are stars,
اربعة من الاجسام المضيئة نجوم
and you can see them there -- little pluses.
ويمكنكم رؤيتها هناك..علامات صغيرة.
This is a star, this is a star, everything else is a galaxy, OK?
هذا نجم، هذا نجم، كل شيء آخر عبارة عن مجرة، حسنا؟
So there's a couple of thousand galaxies
لذا هناك حوالي ألفي
you can see easily with your eye in here.
مجرة يمكنكم رؤيتها بكل سهولة بعيونكم هنا.
And when I look out at particularly this galaxy,
وعندما أحدق النظر على هذه المجرة تحديدا
which looks a lot like ours, I wonder if there's
والتي تبدو كمجرتنا، أتسائل هل
an art design college conference going on,
هناك مؤتمر جاري في كلية فنون التصميم
and intelligent beings there are thinking about, you know,
ومخلوقات عاقلة هناك تفكر في، تعرفون،
what designs they might do, and there might be a few cosmologists
نوع التصميم الذي ستقوم به وهناك بعض علماء الكون
trying to understand where the universe itself came from,
يحاولون فهم نشأة الكون وأصله
and there might even be some in that galaxy looking at ours
وقد يكون هناك حتى في تلك المجرة من ينظر الى مجرتنا
trying to figure out what's going on over here.
ويتسائل عما يجري هناك (اي في مجرتنا).
But there's a lot of other galaxies, and some are nearby,
ولكن هناك الكثير من المجرات وبعضها قريب
and they're kind of the color of the Sun,
ولونها شبيه بلون الشمس
and some are further away and they're a little bluer, and so forth.
وبعضها بعيد وغير واضحه للعيان وهلما جرا.
But one of the questions is -- this should be, to you --
ولكن السؤال..وهو موجه لك..
how come there are so many galaxies?
لماذا هناك الكثير من المجرات؟
Because this represents a very clean fraction of the sky.
لإن ما ترونه يمثل جزء بسيط من السماء.
This is only 1,000 galaxies.
هذه 1000 مجرة فقط.
We think there's on the order -- visible to the Hubble Space Telescope,
نعتقد بأن العدد قد يكون في حدود...يمكن لتلسكوب هابل رصد،
if you had the time to scan it around --
اذا كان عندكم متسع من الوقت، مسح حوالي
about 100 billion galaxies. Right?
100 بليون مجرة، حقا؟
It's a very large number of galaxies.
إنه عدد كبير جدا من المجرات.
And that's roughly how many stars there are in our own galaxy.
وهذا يعادل تقريبا عدد النجوم التي في مجرتنا.
But when you look at some of these regions like this, you'll see
ولكن عندما تنظرون الى بعض هذه المناطق مثل هذا، سترون
more galaxies than stars, which is kind of a conundrum.
مجرات أكثر من نجوم، وهذا أمر محير الى حد ما.
So the question should come to your mind is, what kind of design, you know,
والسؤال الذي يجب أن يكون ماثلا
what kind of creative process and what kind of design
ما هي عمليات الابداع وما هي طرق التصميم
produced the world like that?
التي ينتج عنها مثل ذلك العالم؟
And then I'm going to show you it's actually a lot more complicated.
وسأستعرض عليكم في الواقع بأن الأمر اكثر تعقيدا.
We're going to try and follow it up.
وسنحاول متابعة الامر.
We have a tool that actually helps us out in this study,
في الواقع لدينا أدوات لتعيننا في دراستنا هذه
and that's the fact that the universe is so incredibly big
وهي حقيقة أن الكون هائل جدا
that it's a time machine, in a certain sense.
كأنه آلة زمن على نحو ما.
We draw this set of nested spheres cut away so you see it.
رسمنا لكم هذه المجموعة من المجالات المتداخلة لكي يتسنى لكم رؤيتها.
Put the Earth at the center of the nested spheres,
لنضع الأرض في مركز المجالات المتداخلة
just because that's where we're making observations.
لإنه المكان الذي يتم فيه رصد الكون.
And the moon is only two seconds away, so if you take a picture of the moon
والقمر يبعد عنا ثانيتين فقط، فاذا كنت تأخذ صورة للقمر
using ordinary light, it's the moon two seconds ago, and who cares.
باستخدام النور الطبيعي، فإنه القمر قبل ثانيتين، وليس بالأمر المهم.
Two seconds is like the present.
فثانيتين كأنها الحاضر.
The Sun is eight minutes ago. That's not such a big deal, right,
الشمس قبل ثمانية دقائق. وليس بامر المهم، صحيح.
unless there's solar flares coming then you want to get out the way.
ما لم يكن هناك انفجار شمسي قادم اذا تود أن تبتعد من الطريق.
You'd like to have a little advance warning.
تود أن يكون عندك نظام تحذير متقدم.
But you get out to Jupiter and it's 40 minutes away. It's a problem.
ولكنك تبلغ المشتري وعندها تبعد بحوالي 40 دقيقة. انها مشكلة.
You hear about Mars, it's a problem communicating to Mars
تسمع عن المريخ، الاتصال بالمريخ مشكلة
because it takes light long enough to go there.
لأنه يستغرق الضوء مدة كافية ليصل هناك.
But if you look out to the nearest set of stars,
ولكنك اذا نظرت الى أقرب المجموعات النجمية
to the nearest 40 or 50 stars, it's about 10 years.
الى اقرب 40 او 50 مجموعة، فإنها تبعد 10 سنوات.
So if you take a picture of what's going on, it's 10 years ago.
لذا اذا التقطت صورة عما يحدث هناك فإنها لما حدث قبل عشر سنوات.
But you go and look to the center of the galaxy,
ولكنك اذا نظرت الى مركز المجرة
it's thousands of years ago.
فإنها لما حدث قبل الآف السنوات.
If you look at Andromeda, which is the nearest big galaxy,
اذا نظرت الى أندروميدا، وهي أقرب مجرة كبيرة،
and it's two million years ago.
فإنا قبل مليونين في الماضي.
If you took a picture of the Earth two million years ago,
اذا أخذت صورة للإرض قبل مليونين سنة
there'd be no evidence of humans at all,
لن يكون هناك أي دليل على وجود البشر اطلاقا،
because we don't think there were humans yet.
لإنه كما نظن لم يوجد البشر بعد.
I mean, it just gives you the scale.
أعني، حتى يكون لدينا مرجع قياسي.
With the Hubble Space Telescope, we're looking at
باستخدام تلسكوب هابل، فاننا نرى
hundreds of millions of years to a billion years.
ما يقدر بمئات الى بلايين الاعوام.
But if we were capable to come up with an idea of how to look even further --
ولكن لو تمكنا من ابتكار سبل للنظر الى أبعد من ذلك...
there's some things even further,
فهناك ما هو أبعد من ذلك،
and that was what I did in a lot of my work,
وهو ما قمت به في كثير من أعمالي،
was to develop the techniques -- we could look out back to even earlier
تطوير تقنيات... تمكننا من النظر الى الزمن البعيد،
epochs before there were stars and before there were galaxies,
الى حقبات سبقت النجوم والمجرات،
back to when the universe was hot and dense and very different.
عندما كان الكون ساخنا وشديد الكثافة ومختلف جدا.
And so that's the sort of sequence,
واذا هذا نوع التسلسل
and so I have a more artistic impression of this.
ولذا عندي رسم خيالي لهذا.
There's the galaxy in the middle, which is the Milky Way,
ها هي المجرة في الوسط، مجرة درب اللبانه،
and around that are the Hubble -- you know, nearby kind of galaxies,
وحول ذلك هابل... تعرفون بجنبه، كالمجرة،
and there's a sphere that marks the different times.
وهذا المجال الذي يشير الى الاحقاب الزمنية المختلفة.
And behind that are some more modern galaxies.
وخلف ذلك مزيد من المجرات الحديثة.
You see the whole big picture?
تروه الصورة الاجمالية كاملة؟
The beginning of time is funny -- it's on the outside, right?
بدايات الزمن غريبة...فهي في الخارج، صحيح؟
And then there's a part of the universe we can't see
وهناك جزء من الكون لا نستطيع رؤيته
because it's so dense and so hot, light can't escape.
لإنه من الكثافة والحرارة حتى إن النور لا يتطاير منه.
It's like you can't see to the center of the Sun;
إنه مثل مركز الشمس لا تستطيع رؤيته
you have to use other techniques to know what's going on inside the Sun.
عليك أن تستخدم تقنيات مختلفة لمعرفة ما يتم داخل الشمس.
But you can see the edge of the Sun,
ولكنك تستطيع رؤية حد الشمس،
and the universe gets that way, and you can see that.
وكذلك بالنسبة للكون، يمكنك رؤية أطرافه.
And then you see this sort of model area around the outside,
ومن ثم ترون هذا النوع من مساحة النموذج حول الاطراف،
and that is the radiation coming from the Big Bang,
وهو الاشعاع الناتج من الانفجار الكوني العظيم،
which is actually incredibly uniform.
وهو في الواقع موحد بشكل لا يصدق.
The universe is almost a perfect sphere,
يبدو الكون مثل الشكل الكروي المتكامل
but there are these very tiny variations
ولكن هناك بعض هذه الاختلافات البسيطة
which we show here in great exaggeration.
والتى نبالغ في تمثليها هنا.
And from them in the time sequence we're going to have to go
وسننطلق بهذا التسلسل الزمني، منها،
from these tiny variations to these irregular galaxies and first stars
من هذه الاختلافات البسيطة الى هذه المجرات الغير منظمة الى النجوم الأولى
to these more advanced galaxies, and eventually the solar system, and so forth.
الى المجرات الأكثر تطورا، وأخير الى النظام الشمسي، وهلم جرا.
So it's a big design job,
لذا فهذا نموذج ضخم التصميم
but we'll see about how things are going on.
ولكنه يمكننا من رؤية كيف تسير الامور.
So the way these measurements were done,
فاذا الطريقة التي تمت بها التقديرات هي
there's been a set of satellites, and this is where you get to see.
بمجموعة من الاقمار الصناعية، وبها نتمكن من رؤية الكون.
So there was the COBE satellite, which was launched in 1989,
لذا فكان هناك قمر كوبي والذي دشن في 1989
and we discovered these variations.
وبه تم اكتشاف هذه الاختلافات.
And then in 2000, the MAP satellite was launched -- the WMAP --
ومن ثم دشن قمر ماب في 2000 ...الـ WMAP ...
and it made somewhat better pictures.
والذي أستطاع التقاط صور أكثر وضوحا.
And later this year -- this is the cool stealth version,
وفي وقت لاحق هذا العام، وهذا نموذج قمر صناعي جيد،
the one that actually has some beautiful design features to it,
والذي يحتوي على تصاميم جميلة بمزيد من الميزات
and you should look -- the Planck satellite will be launched,
ويجب عليكم رؤيته... سيتم تدشين قمر بلانك
and it will make very high-resolution maps.
والذي يستطيع التقاط خرائط عالية الدقة.
And that will be the sequence of understanding
وهذا سيكون تسلسل فهم
the very beginning of the universe.
البدايات الأولى لنشأة الكون.
And what we saw was, we saw these variations, and then they told us
وما رأيناه، رأينا هذه الاختلافات، ومن ثم قيل لنا
the secrets, both about the structure of space-time,
الاسرار، عن بنية الفضاء-الزمني،
and about the contents of the universe,
وعن محتويات الكون،
and about how the universe started in its original motions.
وكيف نشأ الكون في بداية حركته الاولى.
So we have this picture, which is quite a spectacular picture,
لذا عندنا هذه الصورة، وهي صورة رائعة
and I'll come back to the beginning, where we're going to have
وسأحدثكم عن البداية لاحقا، عندما تمت
some mysterious process that kicks the universe off at the beginning.
عمليات مبهمة عنا والتي بها نشأ الكون.
And we go through a period of accelerating expansion, and the universe
وننتقل من من مرحلة التوسع المتسارع، والعالم
expands and cools until it gets to the point where it becomes transparent,
يتوسع ويبرد حتى يصل الى مرحلة يصبح لونه شفافا
then to the Dark Ages, and then the first stars turn on,
ثم يتحول الى اللون الاسود وعندها يشهد الكون ميلاد أول النجوم
and they evolve into galaxies, and then later they get to the more expansive galaxies.
وتتطور النجوم الى مجرات وتصبح بعدها ذلك مجرات أكثر اتساعا.
And somewhere around this period is when our solar system started forming.
وفي مكان ما في هذه الفترة يبدأ نظامنا الشمسي في التكون.
And it's maturing up to the present time.
لينضج الى ما عليه في وقتنا الحاضر.
And there's some spectacular things.
وهناك بعض الأشياء المدهشة.
And this wastebasket part, that's to represent
وهذا الجزء من السلة يمثل
what the structure of space-time itself is doing during this period.
ما يحدث لبنية الفضاء-الزمني في خلال هذه الفترة.
And so this is a pretty weird model, right?
ولذا هذا نموذج غريب الى حد ما، صحيح؟
What kind of evidence do we have for that?
ما نوع الدلائل التي عندنا على النموذج؟
So let me show you some of nature's patterns
دعوني أريكم بعض انماط الطبيعة
that are the result of this.
التي هي نتيجة لهذا.
I always think of space-time as being the real substance of space,
دائما انظر الى البعد الفضائي-الزمني كالمضمون الحقيقي للفضاء
and the galaxies and the stars just like the foam on the ocean.
والمجرات والنجوم كمثل زبد المحيط فحسب.
It's a marker of where the interesting waves are and whatever went on.
انها العلامة لتلك الموجات المشوقة وأيما حدث.
So here is the Sloan Digital Sky Survey showing the location of a million galaxies.
لذا هذا المسح لـ Sloan Digital Sky Survey يبين مواقع ملايين المجرات.
So there's a dot on here for every galaxy.
والنقطة الواحدة تمثل كل مجرة.
They go out and point a telescope at the sky, take a picture,
يخرجون بتلسكوباتهم يوجهوها الى السماء, يلتقطون صورة،
identify what are stars and throw them away, look at the galaxies,
يتعرفون على النجوم ثم يمسحوها من الصورة، ينقبون عن المجرات
estimate how far away they are, and plot them up.
وكم تبعد ويضيفونها الى الصورة.
And just put radially they're going out that way.
ويضيفون اتجاه إشعاعها.
And you see these structures, this thing we call the Great Wall,
وترون هذه البنى هذا ما نسميه بالجدار العظيم،
but there are voids and those kinds of stuff, and they kind of fade out
ولكن هناك فراغات وهذا النوع من الاشياء وتخبت رؤيتها
because the telescope isn't sensitive enough to do it.
لإن التلسكوب لا يستطيع التقاطها.
Now I'm going to show you this in 3D.
والآن سأستعرضها بصورة ثلاثية الابعاد.
What happens is, you take pictures
ما يحدث هو عندم تصور
as the Earth rotates, you get a fan across the sky.
في وقت دوران الارض، تلتقط صورة مروحة عبر السماء.
There are some places you can't look because of our own galaxy,
وهناك بعض الاماكن التي لا يمكن رؤيتها بسبب مجرتنا
or because there are no telescopes available to do it.
أو لانه لا توجد تلسكوبات للقيام بذلك.
So the next picture shows you the three-dimensional version of this rotating around.
والصورة التالية تبين نسخة ثلاثية الابعاد لهذا العالم الذي يدور.
Do you see the fan-like scans made across the sky?
هل ترون شبيه المروحه المنطبع عبر السماء؟
Remember, every spot on here is a galaxy, and you see the galaxies,
تذكروا كل نقطة ترونها تمثل مجرة، وترون المجرات،
you know, sort of in our neighborhood, and you sort of see the structure.
تعرفون، كانها في جوار حينا، وكأنكم ترون بنائها.
And you see this thing we call the Great Wall,
وترون هذا الذي نسميه الجدار العظيم،
and you see the complicated structure, and you see these voids.
وترون هذه البنى البالغة التعقيد وترون هذه الفراغات.
There are places where there are no galaxies and there are places
هناك أماكن خالية من المجرات وهناك أماكن
where there are thousands of galaxies clumped together, right.
بها الآف المجرات المتجمعة، صحيح.
So there's an interesting pattern,
لذا فهناك نمط شيق،
but we don't have enough data here to actually see the pattern.
ولكن ليس لدينا بيانات كافية هنا لنرى في الواقع النمط.
We only have a million galaxies, right?
لدينا مليون مجرة، صحيح؟
So we're keeping, like, a million balls in the air
لذا كأننا نبقي على مليون كرة في الفضاء
but, what's going on?
ولكن ماذا يجري؟
There's another survey which is very similar to this,
هناك مسح آخر شبيه بهذا المسح
called the Two-degree Field of View Galaxy Redshift Survey.
يسمى مسح الازاحة الحمراء للمجرة من الدرجة الثانية.
Now we're going to fly through it at warp a million.
الآن نحن في طريقنا للطيران من خلاله بقدر لفة تساوي مليون.
And every time there's a galaxy -- at its location there's a galaxy --
وفي كل مرة تكون هناك مجرة... في موقعه هناك المجرة...
and if we know anything about the galaxy, which we do,
واذا كنا نعلم شيئا عن المجرة، ونحن نعلم،
because there's a redshift measurement and everything,
هناك قياس الازاحة الحمراء وكل شيء،
you put in the type of galaxy and the color,
وتضع نوع المجرة واللون،
so this is the real representation.
لذا فهذا تشبيه حقيقي.
And when you're in the middle of the galaxies
وعندما تكون في وسط المجرات
it's hard to see the pattern; it's like being in the middle of life.
يصعب رؤية النمط، الامر شبيه بمنتصف العمر.
It's hard to see the pattern in the middle of the audience,
انه من الصعب أن ترى النمط وانت في وسط الجمهور،
it's hard to see the pattern of this.
انه صعب ان ترى نمط هذا.
So we're going to go out and swing around and look back at this.
لذا سنخرج ونلتف لننظر اليه من الخلف.
And you'll see, first, the structure of the survey,
وسترون في البداية بنية المسح
and then you'll start seeing the structure of the galaxies
ومن ثم ستبدؤون برؤية بنية المجرات
that we see out there.
التي نراها هناك في الخارج.
So again, you can see the extension of this Great Wall of galaxies showing up here.
لذا مرة أخرى، سترون امتداد هذا الجدار العظيم من المجرات تظهر هناك.
But you can see the voids,
ولكنكم سترون الفراغات،
you can see the complicated structure, and you say,
يمكنكم رؤية البنية المعقدة وستقولون،
well, how did this happen?
حسنا، كيف حدث هذا؟
Suppose you're the cosmic designer.
لنفترض بأنك انت مصمم الكون.
How are you going to put galaxies out there in a pattern like that?
كيف ستضع المجرات هناك في نمط كهذا؟
It's not just throwing them out at random.
الامر ليس مجرد رميها هناك بعشوائية.
There's a more complicated process going on here.
هنالك المزيد من المراحل المعقدة التي تحدث هناك.
How are you going to end up doing that?
كيف سينتهي بك المطاف عمل ذلك؟
And so now we're in for some serious play.
واذا نحن في بعض اللعب الجاد.
That is, we have to seriously play God,
وهذا اللعب يشبه لعب الخالق،
not just change people's lives, but make the universe, right.
ليس مجرد احداث تغيير في حياة الناس، بل صنع الكون، صح.
So if that's your responsibility, how are you going to do that?
لذا فاذا كانت هذه هي مسؤليتك، كيف ستقوم بالامر؟
What's the kind of technique?
ما نوع التقنية المناسبة؟
What's the kind of thing you're going to do?
ما هو النوع الشيء الذي ستقوم به؟
So I'm going to show you the results of a very large-scale simulation
لذا ساستعرض عليكم نتائج محاكاة على نطاق واسع جدا
of what we think the universe might be like, using, essentially,
ما نعتقد ما يمكن ان يكون عليه الكون، باستخدام
some of the play principles and some of the design principles that,
في الواقع بعض مباديء اللعب والتصميم، التي،
you know, humans have labored so hard to pick up,
تعرفون، عمل البشر جاهدين لتعلمها،
but apparently nature knew how to do at the beginning.
ولكن كما يبدو عرفتها الطبيعة منذ البداية.
And that is, you start out with very simple ingredients
وهي تقوم في البداية على مكونات اساسية بسيطة
and some simple rules,
وبعض القوانين البسيطة،
but you have to have enough ingredients to make it complicated.
ولكن يجب ان يكون بحوزتكم مكونات كافية لتحقيق التعقيد.
And then you put in some randomness,
ومن ثم تضعون بعض العشوائية
some fluctuations and some randomness,
وبعض التقلبات وبعض العشوائية
and realize a whole bunch of different representations.
ومن ثم تتحقق عددا من الثمثيلات المختلفة.
So what I'm going to do is show you
لذا ما سأقوم به هو العرض عليكم
the distribution of matter as a function of scales.
توزيع المادة كمعادلة قياسية.
We're going to zoom in, but this is a plot of what it is.
وسنضخم الصورة لنوضح أكثر التوزيع.
And we had to add one more thing to make the universe come out right.
وعلينا إضافة شيء آخر ليتضح الكون بشكل أفضل.
It's called dark matter.
إنه يعرف بالمادة السوداء.
That is matter that doesn't interact with light
هذه المادة لا تتفاعال والنور،
the typical way that ordinary matter does,
كبقية المواد التي تتفاعل والنور،
the way the light's shining on me or on the stage.
بالطريقة التي يضيء فيها النور علينا أو على المسرح.
It's transparent to light, but in order for you to see it,
يمر النور من خلال المادة السوادء ولرؤيتها
we're going to make it white. OK?
سنلونها باللون الابيض، صحيح؟
So the stuff that's in this picture that's white, that is the dark matter.
لذا فهذه الاشياء التي لونها ابيض في هذه الصورة هي المادة السوداء.
It should be called invisible matter,
ويجب ان تسمى بالمادة الخفية،
but the dark matter we've made visible.
وحولنا هذه المادة المخفية الى مادة مرئية.
And the stuff that is in the yellow color,
والاشياء التي لونها أصفر
that is the ordinary kind of matter that's turned into stars and galaxies.
هي المواد الاعتيادية التي تحولت الى نجوم ومجرات.
So I'll show you the next movie.
وسأريكم الفلم التالي.
So this -- we're going to zoom in.
وهذا...سأكبر الصورة أكثر.
Notice this pattern and pay attention to this pattern.
لاحظوا هذا الشكل وانتبهوا لهذا النمط.
We're going to zoom in and zoom in.
وسنكبر الصورة أكبر وأكبر.
And you'll see there are all these filaments and structures and voids.
وسترون كل هذا الخطوط والبنى والفراغات.
And when a number of filaments come together in a knot,
وعندما تتشابك الخيوط في عقدة،
that makes a supercluster of galaxies.
تشكل مجموعة كتل هائلة من المجرات.
This one we're zooming in on
سنكبر الصورة على هذه الواحدة
is somewhere between 100,000 and a million galaxies in that small region.
والتي تقدر بحوالي 100 الف الى مليون مجرة في المنطقة الصغيرة.
So we live in the boonies.
لذا نعيش بعيدا في الهامش.
We don't live in the center of the solar system,
لا نعيش في مركز النظام الشمسي،
we don't live in the center of the galaxy
لا نعيش في مركز المجرة
and our galaxy's not in the center of the cluster.
ومجرتنا ليست في مركز العقدة.
So we're zooming in.
لذا نكبر الصورة أكثر.
This is a region which probably has more than 100,000,
تحتوي هذه المنطقة على ما يقارب 100 الف
on the order of a million galaxies in that region.
مليون مجرة.
We're going to keep zooming in. OK.
وسنستمر في تكبير الصورة. حسنا.
And so I forgot to tell you the scale.
ولذا نسيت أن أخبركم عن وحدة الوزن.
A parsec is 3.26 light years.
بارسيك "A parsec" يساوي 3.26 سنة ضوئية.
So a gigaparsec is three billion light years -- that's the scale.
ولذا الجيجابارسيك "gigaparsec" يساوي 3 بلايين سنة ضوئية..وهذه هي وحدة القياس.
So it takes light three billion years to travel over that distance.
لذا يستغرق الضوء 3 بلايين سنة ضوئية لعبور تلك المسافة.
Now we're into a distance sort of between here and here.
نحن الآن في مسافة نقدرها بين هنا وهناك.
That's the distance between us and Andromeda, right?
هذه هي المسافة بيننا وبين مجرة أندرميدا، صحيح؟
These little specks that you're seeing in here, they're galaxies.
هذه البقع الصغيرة التي ترونها هنا هي عبارة عن مجرات.
Now we're going to zoom back out,
الآن سنصغر الصورة راجعين،
and you can see this structure that,
وتستطيعون رؤية هذه البنية التي
when we get very far out, looks very regular,
عندما تبتعدون عنها كثيرا تبدو إعتيادية جدا.
but it's made up of a lot of irregular variations.
ولكنها تحتوي على الكثير من التنوعات الغير منظمة.
So they're simple building blocks.
لذا فهي هياكل بناء بسيطة.
There's a very simple fluid to begin with.
فهي سائل بسيط جدا في البداية.
It's got dark matter, it's got ordinary matter,
تحتوي على مادة سوداء، ومادة اعتيادية.
it's got photons and it's got neutrinos,
تحتوي على فتونات وعلى نيترينوات،
which don't play much role in the later part of the universe.
والتي لا تقوم بدور اساسي في الجزء اللاحق للكون.
And it's just a simple fluid and it, over time,
وهو مجرد سائل بسيط ومع مرور الزمن
develops into this complicated structure.
تطور الى بنية معقدة التركيب.
And so you know when you first saw this picture,
وعند رؤيتكم هذه الصورة لأول مرة
it didn't mean quite so much to you.
لم تعني لكم الكثير.
Here you're looking across one percent of the volume of the visible universe
تشاهدون عبر هذا حوالي 1% من حجم الكون المرئي
and you're seeing billions of galaxies, right, and nodes,
وترون بلايين المجرات، صحيح، والعقد،
but you realize they're not even the main structure.
ولكن تدركون بأنه ليس البناء الأساس للكون.
There's a framework, which is the dark matter, the invisible matter,
هناك اطر المادة السوداء، المادة الغير مرئية،
that's out there that's actually holding it all together.
التي في الخارج هناك والتي في الواقع تمسك بكل شيء.
So let's fly through it, and you can see how much harder it is
لذا دعونا نطير فيها وترون كم هو صعب
when you're in the middle of something to figure this out.
معرفة ماهية الشيء عندما تكون في وسطه.
So here's that same end result.
لذا فالنتيجة النهائية هي نفسها.
You see a filament,
ترون خيط
you see the light is the invisible matter,
ترون النور إنه المادة الغير مرئية،
and the yellow is the stars or the galaxies showing up.
والاصفر عبارة عن النجوم أو المجرات التي تطلع.
And we're going to fly around, and we'll fly around,
وسنحلق حول، وسنحلق حول
and you'll see occasionally a couple of filaments intersect,
وسترون في بعض الاحيان تتشابك الخيوط
and you get a large cluster of galaxies.
وعندها تكون كتلة هائلة من المجرات.
And then we'll fly in to where the very large cluster is,
ومن ثم سنحلق الى موقع الكتلة الهائلة
and you can see what it looks like.
وتستطيعون رؤية شكلها.
And so from inside, it doesn't look very complicated, right?
ومن الداخل لا تبدو بإنها بالغة التعقيد، صحيح؟
It's only when you look at it at a very large scale,
عندم تنظر إليها من بعد فقط
and explore it and so forth, you realize it's a very intricate,
وتحاول إكتشافها تدرك كم هي معقدة
complicated kind of a design, right?
التركيب وبالغة الدقة في التصميم، صحيح؟
And it's grown up in some kind of way.
وبأنها تنمو بطريقة ما.
So the question is,
فالسؤال اذا،
how hard would it be to assemble this, right?
هل من الصعوبة بمكان تجميع مثل هذا، صحيح؟
How big a contractor team would you need
ما هو حجم المقاول الذي تحتاجه
to put this universe together, right?
لتجميع هذا الكون، صحيح؟
That's the issue, right?
هذه هي القضية، صحيح؟
And so here we are.
ولذا نحن هنا.
You see how the filament --
ترون كيف الخطوط ..
you see how several filaments are coming together,
ترون كيف تتجمع عدة خيوط،
therefore making this supercluster of galaxies.
مشكلة بذلك هذه الكتلة الهائلة من المجرات.
And you have to understand, this is not how it would actually look
وعليكم معرفة بأنها ليست كما تبدو في الواقع
if you -- first, you can't travel this fast,
اذ انتم.. بدأ، لا تستطيعون السفر بهذه السرعة
everything would be distorted,
لإنه سيكون كل شيء مشوها،
but this is using simple rendering and graphic arts kind of stuff.
ولكن باستخدام الوسائط الفنية يمكننا السفر حسيا.
This is how, if you took billions of years to go around,
هكذ، لو أمكنكم السفر حولها في بلايين الاعوام،
it might look to you, right?
ستبدو لكم، صحيح؟
And if you could see invisible matter, too.
وكذلك اذا أمكنكم رؤية المادة الغير مرئية.
And so the idea is, you know, how would you put together the universe
والفكرة إذا كيف تضع الكون في قالب واحد
in a very simple way?
بطريقة سهلة للغاية؟
We're going to start and realize that the entire visible universe,
سنبدأ بإدراك حقيقة أن كل الكون المرئي
everything we can see in every direction with the Hubble Space Telescope
كل ما يمكننا مشاهدته على كل الاتجاهات بتلسكوب هابل
plus our other instruments,
وبالمعدات الأخرى،
was once in a region that was smaller than an atom.
كان في الماضي في نقطة أصغر من حجم الذرة.
It started with tiny quantum mechanical fluctuations,
بدأ الكون بتغير كمي بسيط
but expanding at a tremendous rate.
ولكنه توسع بمعدل هائل جدا.
And those fluctuations
وهذه التغيرات
were stretched to astronomical sizes, and those fluctuations
تمددت الى أحجام خيالية، وهذه التغيرات
eventually are the things we see in the cosmic microwave background.
هي التي نراها الآن على شكل موجات كونية صغيرة تحيط بالكون.
And then we needed some way to turn those fluctuations into galaxies
وبطريقة أو أخرى نحتاج الى تحويل هذه التغيرات الى مجرات
and clusters of galaxies and make these kinds of structures go on.
وكتل من المجرات وهذا النوع من البناء القادر على الاستمرار.
So I'm going to show you a smaller simulation.
لذا سأستعرض عليكم محاكاة لما حدث.
This simulation was run on 1,000 processors for a month
هذه المحاكاة البسيطة تم تنفيذها على ألف معالج حاسوب ولمدة شهر
in order to make just this simple visible one.
لعرض الجانب المرئي من الكون فقط.
So I'm going to show you one
لذا سأستعرض عليكم واحدة
that can be run on a desktop in two days in the next picture.
يمكن تشغيلها على حاسوب شخصي في يومين في الصورة التالية.
So you start out with teeny fluctuations
لذا البداية من هذه التغيرات الطفيفة
when the universe was at this point,
عندما كان الكون عند هذه النقطة
now four times smaller, and so forth.
الآن عندما كان حجمه ربع ما عليه الآن، وهلما جرا.
And you start seeing these networks, this cosmic web of structure forming.
وتبدو هذه الشبكات في الظهور، بنية هذه الشبكات الكونية تتشكل.
And this is a simple one, because it doesn't have the ordinary matter
وفي هذه المرحلة الامر بسيط لإنها لا تحتوي على المواد الاعتيادية
and it just has the dark matter in it.
تحتوي على المادة السوداء فقط.
And you see how the dark matter lumps up,
وترون كيف تتكتل المادة السوداء
and the ordinary matter just trails along behind.
والمواد الاعتيادية تأتي بعيدها فقط.
So there it is.
لذا هذه هي البداية.
At the beginning it's very uniform.
في البداية كانت موحدة جدا.
The fluctuations are a part in 100,000.
التغيرات تتعاقب كل 100 الف.
There are a few peaks that are a part in 10,000,
هناك بعض القمم التي تتعاقب كل 10 الآف
and then over billions of years, gravity just pulls in.
ومن ثم خلال بلايين الأعوام، تقوم الجاذبية بسحبها الى الداخل.
This is light over density, pulls the material around in.
هذا نور على الكثافة يسحب كل المواد التي حوله.
That pulls in more material and pulls in more material.
وهذه بدوره يسحب المزيد من المواد اليه.
But the distances on the universe are so large
ولكن المسافات في الكون هائلة
and the time scales are so large that it takes a long time for this to form.
والبعد الزمني هائل جدا حتى إن الأمر يستغرق مدة طويلة جدا ليتشكل هذا.
And it keeps forming until the universe is roughly about half the size it is now,
ويستمر في التشكل حتى يصبح الكون حوالي نصف حجمه الآن
in terms of its expansion.
من حيث توسعه.
And at that point, the universe mysteriously starts accelerating
وعندها وبطريقة غامضة تسارع الكون يبدأ
its expansion and cuts off the formation of larger-scale structure.
في الزيادة ويتوقف تشكل البنى الضخمة.
So we're just seeing as large a scale structure as we can see,
لذلك نحن نرى مجرد اكبر بناء يمكننا رؤيته،
and then only things that have started forming already
وبعد ذلك الأشياء التي بدأت بالفعل تتشكل فحسب
are going to form, and then from then on it's going to go on.
ستتشكل ومن ثم تتشكل وستستمر على ذلك.
So we're able to do the simulation, but this is two days on a desktop.
لذا يمكننا محاكاة ما يحدث ولكن هذا عمل يومين على حاسوب شخصي.
We need, you know, 30 days on 1,000 processors
نحتاج الى 30 يوما و1000 حاسوب
to do the kind of simulation that I showed you before.
للقيام بنوع المحاكاة التي استعرضتها عليكم سابقا.
So we have an idea of how to play seriously, creating the universe
لذا عندنا فكرة جادة كيف يمكننا خلق كون،
by starting with essentially less than an eyedrop full of material,
بداً في الاساس باستخدام مواد تقل عما تحتويه مواد في حجم قطرة عين
and we create everything we can see in any direction, right,
ونخلق كل شيء يمكننا رؤيته على كل الاتجاهات، صحيح
from almost nothing -- that is, something extremely tiny,
من لا شيء تقريبا.. شيء في منتهى الصغر
extremely small -- and it is almost perfect,
صغير جدا.. ويقترب من الكمال،
except it has these tiny fluctuations at a part in 100,000 level,
عدا إنه يتغير تغيرا طفيفا بمقدار بـ100 ألف في الجزء
which turn out to produce the interesting patterns and designs we see,
وهذا التغير البسيط نتج عنه أنماط وتصاميم عجيبة كما نراها
that is, galaxies and stars and so forth.
وهي عبارة عن مجرات ونجوم وهلما جرا.
So we have a model, and we can calculate it, and we can use it
لذلك عندنا نموذج نستطيع تقديره ومن ثم استخدامه
to make designs of what we think the universe really looks like.
لعمل تصاميم للشكل الحقيقي للكون، كما نعتقد.
And that design is sort of way beyond
وتبين بأن التصميم يختلف تماما
what our original imagination ever was.
عما تخليناه في البداية.
So this is what we started with 15 years ago,
لذلك هذا هو الشكل الذي بدأنا به قبل 15 عام،
with the Cosmic Background Explorer -- made the map on the upper right,
واستطاع المسبار الفضائي "مستكشف الخلفية الكونية" رسم الخريطة التي على أعلى اليمين
which basically showed us that there were large-scale fluctuations,
واللتي تبين بأنه كانت هناك تقلبات واسعة النطاق،
and actually fluctuations on several scales. You can kind of see that.
التقلبات في الواقع على عدة نطاقات. يمكنكم رؤية ذلك الى حد ما.
Since then we've had WMAP,
ومنذ حينه طورنا مسبار WMAP
which just gives us higher angular resolution.
والذي رسم خرائط أكثر دقة.
We see the same large-scale structure,
نرى نفس الهياكل الضخمة
but we see additional small-scale structure.
ولكن بالاضافة الى ذلك نفس الهياكل الاقل ضخامة.
And on the bottom right is if the satellite had flipped upside down
والموقع الذي في أدنى يمين الخريطة إذا قلبنا القمر الصناعي رأس على عقب
and mapped the Earth, what kind of a map we would have got of the Earth.
ورسمنا خريطة الارض، أي نوع من الخرائط ستكون عندنا عن الأرض.
You can see, well, you can, kind of pick out
يمكنكم رؤية، حسنا، الى حد ما
all the major continents, but that's about it.
كل القارات الاساسية، وهذا ما يمكننا رؤيته فحسب.
But what we're hoping when we get to Planck, we'll have resolution
ولكن نأمل بأن يستطيع مسبار Planck بأن يرسم خرائط افضل من ذلك
about equivalent to the resolution you see of the Earth there,
كاللتي تعادل ما ترونه عن الأرض هناك
where you can really see the complicated pattern that exists on the Earth.
حيث يمكنكم حقا رؤية الانماط المعقدة الموجودة على الارض.
And you can also tell, because of the sharp edges
ويمكنكم أيضا معرفة، بسبب الحواف الحادة
and the way things fit together, there are some non-linear processes.
وبالطريقة اللتي تتركب فيها طبقات الارض مع بعضها البعض بأن هناك عمليا غير خطية
Geology has these effects,
فعلم الارض يقودك الى إدراك
which is moving the plates around and so forth.
حقيقة أن طبقات الارض تتحرك من مكان الى آخر.
You can see that just from the map alone.
يمكنكم رؤية كل ذلك من هذه الخريطة وحدها.
We want to get to the point in our maps of the early universe
نود أن نرسم خرائط توضح بدايات عهد الكون
we can see whether there are any non-linear effects
لمعرفة هل تمت عمليات غير خطية في البداية
that are starting to move, to modify, and are giving us a hint about how
وهل بدأت بالتحرك من مكان الى آخر، وهل يساعدنا ذلك الى معرفة كيف
space-time itself was actually created at the beginning moments.
نشأ البعد الزماني-الفضائي في اللحظات الأولى.
So that's where we are today,
أذا هذا واقع اليوم
and that's what I wanted to give you a flavor of.
وهذا ما أحببت ان استعرضه عليكم في هذه العجالة.
Give you a different view about what the design
أقدم رؤية مختلفة عن التصميم
and what everything else looks like.
وكيف تبدو كل الاشياء الأخرى.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)